A Guide to the Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge Correspondence 1810-1861
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Ellen Coolidge to Henry S. Randall and others, 1845, 1856-1858 (Box 3)
  a 102 page volume (also on microfilm M-1238) containing handwritten copies of her letters to Randall and others concerning the life of Thomas Jefferson, especially his financial problems (pp. 3-8); his religious ideas (pp. 9-19); his presidency and character (pp. 21-27) from a letter to the German historian Maumur in 1845; blanks in his correspondence (pp. 28-30); the Carr family (pp. 31-35); corrections to Randall's book (pp. 36-37); Monticello (pp. 38-39); Aunt Mary Eppes (p. 41); the finances of Jefferson and Col. Thomas Mann Randolph (pp. 42-50); Poplar Forest (pp. 51-56); the slave Wormley (p. 57); the relationship between Thomas Jefferson and Thomas Mann Randolph (pp. 58-61); the wife of Thomas Jefferson, Martha Wayles Skelton (pp. 66-67); the missing letters of Thomas Jefferson to Martha Jefferson Randolph (pp. 68-72); the death of Thomas Jefferson (pp. 74-75); Martha Randolph's death (pp. 81-87); the grave of Thomas Jefferson (pp. 88-90); and rumors of slave children born to Thomas Jefferson (pp. 98-102).
- Ellen Coolidge to [?] [post 1836] (Box 3)
  a single leaf from a letter containing her melancholy memories of her mother and grandfather and other dead friends written while on a voyage, she reflects upon the sterling quality of their characters, her mother's love and talent for music, and concludes that the only defect in the character of her grandfather was religion or consistent piety, that was choked out by "the sceptical spirit of the age" and "miscalled professors of religion"
- Ellen Coolidge to Elizabeth [?] [post 1861] July 13 (Box 3)
  Expresses her sorrow over being separated from her relatives by the Civil War, tells about the bitter hatred in Boston for the South, reveals her disapproval of secession and the attack on Fort Sumter, but still feels like a daughter of the South and Virginia where "state feeling is strongest"
- envelope leaf with a postscript of a letter to Martha Randolph n.d. (Box 3)
- two covers for letters to Ellen and Joseph Coolidge with no content n.d. (Box 3)
- Thomas Jefferson, Ballad and Songs ante 1826, 9090-c
  Poetry copied by Thomas Jefferson:
  "Last Valentines day when bright Phoebus shone clear"
  "La Primavera" (in Italian)
  "La Par[t]enza" (in Italian)